<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The reformed Spaniard to all reformed Churches, embracing the true faith, wheresoeuer dispersed on the face of the earth: in speciall, to the most reuerend archbishops, reuerend bishops, and worshipfull doctors, and pastors, now gathered together in the venerable Synode at London, this yeare of our Lord, 1621. Iohn de Nicholas &amp; Sacharles, Doctor of Physicke, wisheth health in our Lord. First published by the author in Latine, and now thence faithfully translated into English.</title>
            <title>Hispanus reformatus. English</title>
            <author>Nicolás, Juan de.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68501</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18530.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101132</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836956</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836956</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1256</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68501)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1256)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 967:19, 1732:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The reformed Spaniard to all reformed Churches, embracing the true faith, wheresoeuer dispersed on the face of the earth: in speciall, to the most reuerend archbishops, reuerend bishops, and worshipfull doctors, and pastors, now gathered together in the venerable Synode at London, this yeare of our Lord, 1621. Iohn de Nicholas &amp; Sacharles, Doctor of Physicke, wisheth health in our Lord. First published by the author in Latine, and now thence faithfully translated into English.</title>
                  <title>Hispanus reformatus. English</title>
                  <author>Nicolás, Juan de.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by for [sic] Walter Burre, and are to be sold at his shop in Paules Church-yard, at the signe of the Crane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Hispanus reformatus.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴ (-A1,E4).</note>
                  <note>This edition has C2r catchword: Heere-.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 18530 on UMI microfilm reel 967.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 967 and at reel 1732 (same copy filmed twice).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1256:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE REFORMED SPANIARD: <hi>To all reformed Churches, embracing the true</hi> Faith, whereſoeuer diſperſed on the <hi>Face of the Earth:</hi> In ſpeciall, To the moſt Reuerend Arch-<hi>Biſhops, Reuerend Biſhops, and Worſhipfull Doctors,</hi> and Paſtors, now gathered together in the venerable Synode at <hi>London,</hi> this yeare of our Lord, 1621.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn de Nicholas &amp; Sacharles, Doctor of Phyſicke, wiſheth health in our</hi> LORD.</p>
            <p>Firſt publiſhed by the Author in Latine, and <hi>now thence faithfully Tranſlated into Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by for Walter Burre, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Paules Church-yard, at the ſigne of the Crane, 1621.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1256:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1256:2"/>
            <head>THE REFORMED SPANIARD.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Declareth the reaſons and motiues, by</hi> which he was induced to forſake the Romiſh Church.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I be by byrth a Spaniard, and cannot deny but that with my Nurſes milke I haue ſucked in the corruptions of popery; though my whole Infancy, child-hoode and youth, hath bene tainted with the dregges of ſuch my education: yet no ſooner was I come to yeeres of diſcretion, but I beganne to ſuſpect the turning of bread and wine into the very ſubſtance of the Body and blood of our Sauiour, to be a meere fiction, much like (both in want of ground, &amp; in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked illuſions) to the coyner thereof, the Antichriſt of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The beginning of my ſuſpition was, in that our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, <hi>Bartholmew Hernandez,</hi> a moſt learned man, in his publique Lectures at <hi>Ilerda</hi> in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> in the yeere of our Lord, 1596. did teach vs being his Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, to the number of aboue 200. that God, by his ordinary power, cannot put one and the ſame body in diuers places at the ſame inſtant of time. This, quoth he, implyeth contradiction, as at once ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and not ſuppoſing a bodie. For by taking away.
<pb facs="tcp:1256:3"/>from any body, the proper paſſion of a body; namely the poſſeſſing one place, thence followeth neceſſarily the deſtruction and aboliſhment of the forme, nature and eſſence of the body it ſelf: Foraſmuch as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of occupying one place, floweth of neceſſitie from the very forme and nature of a body, nor can by Gods ordinary power be ſeparated there-from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deſtroying the ſubiect it ſelfe, on which it depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth. And that this confining to one place, is a true property, or proper paſſion of a body, it is euident, in that it ſuiteth with bodies vniuerſally, only &amp; alwaies, and is reciprocated with a body. But whether God by his abſolute and extraordinary power (whereby hee doth what he can do, or atchiueth a work, then which he cannot performe a greater or more perfect) can do a work, which contradicteth it ſelfe, my ſaid Maſter would neither auouch, nor deny. This quoth he, is to mee a bottomeleſſe Sea, whereinto I dare not launch with the ſmal cock-boat of my poore vnderſtanding. Yet withall he conſtantly affirmed, that God neuer v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed this his abſolute power, but in one work only, and that was the Incarnating of his Sonne. Then which he ſaid, that God cannot produce a more excellent and more perfect exploit: whereas in the production of this whol world, and of the inuiſible, and viſible crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the ſame, it is otherwiſe. For God, if it had pleaſed him, could haue created much more glorious Angels, men more excellent, and brighter or better heauens then theſe which he hath made.</p>
            <p>Out of this Doctrine thus deliuered by our Maſter, there aroſe in my minde no ſmall ſcruple, whence I forthwith, though then but young, reaſoned with my
<pb facs="tcp:1256:3"/>ſelf, inferring this ſame <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth to put the bodyof our Lord in many millions of places at the ſame inſtant of time, not to be of God, much leſſe performable by the ſacrificing Prieſts. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, thought I, it neuer came from Gods ordinary power, by which he doth nothing implying contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; no, nor from his abſolute and extraordinary, which (as my Maſter would haue it) was neuer vſed but in the worke of Chriſts Incarnation. And ſo I concluded, that <hi>Tranſubstantiation</hi> is no worke of Gods making.</p>
            <p>To deliuer freely what afterward I thought, my coniecture is, that this my Maſter, intending here to expreſſe himſelfe cautelouſly, did on purpoſe ſpeake perplexedly. For ſwallowing this pebble ſtone of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and being not able to concoct it, he checked his ſtomacke downe as much as he could to keepe it from a dangerous vomit: and in a word to tell his caſe, he was faine to windevp himſelfe in the ſnare of doubtfull words, that he might eſcape the ſnare of the <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition.</hi> The truth is, this learned man, who knew well enough, white from blacke, ſhould boldly haue affirmed, that Almighty God, neither by ordinary nor extraordinary power, can doe thoſe things, that are contradictory to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, &amp; therefore cannot ſet one and the ſame body in diuers places at the ſame inſtant. And that, not by reaſon of any want of actiue power in God, who is omnipotent; but by defect of paſſiue power in the creature (if ſuch fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions may be called creatures) which cannot ſuffer their eſſentiall and concomitant properties be tome away from the maine ſtocke, without the deſtruction
<pb facs="tcp:1256:4"/>of the whole nature and eſſence of the ſubiect, which natheleſſe is heere ſuppoſed to remaine entyre. For what can be more abſurd, then if I ſhold ſay, I preſent vnto you a man, from whom I will notwithſtanding take away the facultie of reaſon? which is as much as, behold here a man, no man: or, ſpeaking of a Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricall circle, I ſhould inſtance in a circle, whoſe beams I would imagine to be vnequalled one to the other. I am deeply touched with ſorow, for that hearing this voyce, whereby God cald me, I notwithſtanding, did not ceaſe to harden mine owne heart againſt it, for the ſpace of 9. yeares after; ſtil keeping my wont of ſaying Maſſes, of hearing auricular confeſſions, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a fierce maintainer of that erroneous Religion. When I firſt put on the Cowle (which I vndertooke in the order of Saint <hi>Hierome,</hi> the moſt renowned in <hi>Spaine</hi>) I was not full ſeuenteene yeares of age: in which regard I may be the more excuſed, if, for want of ripeneſſe in iudgement, I tooke not a fitter courſe for my ſoules health. Yet at that age was I ſet in good forwardneſſe in the <hi>Latine</hi> and <hi>Greeke</hi> Languages, in <hi>Rhetorique,</hi> and <hi>Poetry,</hi> in <hi>Logique,</hi> and the whole courſe of <hi>Ariſtotles Philoſophie;</hi> and moreouer, I had made alſo ſome entrance into the ſtudie of <hi>Phyſicke.</hi> Beeing ſetled in the Monaſterie, I diuerted my ſelfe wholly to Diuinity, and imployed me in the daily rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Scriptures. Which that I might the more diligently attend, I was ſent to the famouſe and rich Colledge of Saint <hi>Laurence</hi> in the <hi>Eſcuriall,</hi> founded by King <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond: and in preſence of King <hi>Philip</hi> the third, I ſang that Maſſe, which was my firſt hanſell.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1256:4"/>
I nor may, nor can conceale, that all that long time, whileſt I was a Maſſ-monger, I found no ioy, no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, no quiet in my minde, nor peace of conſcience, by communicating in the Maſſe, &amp; by that vnbloody ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, ſo called; howſoeuer I had vſed more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary diligence in <hi>fore-examining my ſelfe,</hi> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth vs, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28 and in premiſing au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricular Confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the Pope willeth vs. When there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by woful experience I found daily more &amp; more, that I could not ſay with the bleſſed Apoſtle, <hi>our reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing is this, the teſtimony of our Conſcience,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. And when as I could not finde in the holy Scriptures, any mention or proofe of the Maſſe, of <hi>Tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,</hi> of the vnbloody ſacrifice, or of Prieſts appointed to ſuch a function, I ſet vp my reſt concerning the Maſſe, to let it paſſe, and meddle no more with it.</p>
            <p>The more was I encouraged to deny <hi>Tranſubstanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,</hi> and to giue ouer the Maſſing Trade, not onely by my Maſters fore-recited Doctrine, which I care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully chewed vpon whileſt I remained in the Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but alſo for that I had obſerued, that he good man, would neuer be brought to ſay Maſſe himſelfe, though he were Prieſted, and had beene by his moſt worthy friends thereto intreated. To whom he was wont to giue this wary anſwer, that he was neuer able to beare in minde, or to learne by heart, the many ceremonies of the Maſſe, whereupon, if he ſhould vndertake that action, he doubted the ſacrifice of the Maſſe, would be marred by the laughter of the by-ſtanders beholding him. In this his ſlye anſwere, geſtured not without a ſmile, me thinks I ſee one thing giuen out in word, and another locked vp within his breſt. Without doubt
<pb facs="tcp:1256:5"/>he in this gaue way to the common weakneſſe of thoſe that put him to the queſtion, being vnwilling that they ſhould take any ſcandall at him. For, as for his priuate Iudgement, his Dictates, before mentioned, ſhew plainely that he had no ſmall ſcruple ſticking in his minde, which could not eaſily be pulled out; and that his ſuſpition againſt <hi>Tranſubstantiation</hi> had taken ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deep root in him: and therefore he could not finde in his heart to vndergo the atchieuement of the Maſſe: inaſmuch as he being perſwaded againſt it, or at leaſt doubting of it, could not haue ſuch intention of Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, as is required in the very act thereof.</p>
            <p>Another motiue draue me further from the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church; namely, that the Pope, being a Creature, da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to iudge the Law of his Creator, euen that Law, by which himſelf is to be iudged at the latter day. For inſted of the firſt Commandement of the Decalogue, written by the finger of God, he hath ſubſtituted and obtruded another vnto the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Nation.</p>
            <p>To ſpeake more plainly, the firſt Commandement of the tenne, written in Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> is this, <hi>Thou ſhalt haue none other Gods but me.</hi> This Commandement the <hi>Spanyards</hi> haue not in their vulgar, the common people heare no newes of it. What then is the firſt Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement which the people in <hi>Spain,</hi> are taught to repeat? Forſooth this, <hi>Amor a Dios ſobre todas las coſas: To loue God aboue all things.</hi> I deny not this to be Gods commandement, yea the grand Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, being the pith and ſum of the whole firſt Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. But if it be lawfull to put out any particular Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and to place this inſtead thereof, why in like maner doe they not in the <hi>Spaniſh Catechiſme</hi> blot
<pb facs="tcp:1256:5"/>out ſome one of the Commandements in the ſecond Table, and put, in ſtead of it, <hi>Thou ſhalt loue thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as thy ſelfe;</hi> which is the ſumme of the ſecond Table? Theſe are, without queſtion they are, two ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall precepts, which in no wiſe exclude any of the ten particular Commandements. And verily no man can loue God aboue all, and his neighbor as himſelfe, vnleſſe he moſt exactly keepe all thoſe ten Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements. <hi>Yee are my friends if ye doe whatſoeuer I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.14.</p>
            <p>But as for the ſecond Commandement, ſo ratified by our great and dreadfull God, partly by promiſes, and partly by threats, ſtyling himſelfe <hi>a iealous God,</hi> and therein forbidding the worſhipping, ſeruing, or falling downe to grauen ſhapes, or likeneſſes of any thing in heauen, or in earth, or in the waters beneath the earth, and ſo condemning all Idolatry, and <hi>Icono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,</hi> that is, Image-worſhip; this Commandement, I ſay, is by the ſon of perdition cancelled, and concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, not onely from vs poore <hi>Spanyards,</hi> but alſo from the <hi>Italian, French,</hi> and al other <hi>Romaniſing</hi> Churches. Let him that hath beene thus bold to blot out Gods words, take heed leſt his own name be blotted out of the Booke of life, according to the threat in the end of Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Reuelation.</p>
            <p>Think other men as they pleaſe, euery one according to the ſway of his priuate apprehenſions: for my part, if there were no other plague in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but this, that the Pope hath preſumed to change the firſt Commandement, &amp; to nimme away the ſecond, both of them beeing precepts twiſe written with the
<pb facs="tcp:1256:6"/>finger of God, and twiſe deliuered to <hi>Moſes</hi> with many ſignes and miracles, I ſhall neuer hope well of thoſe, that make the Pope their Idoll, vnleſſe they ſhall by Gods grace repent,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 5.29.</note> and learne, <hi>that it is better to obey God, then men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer, another motiue to driue me from Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry was; That, whereas our Lord and Sauiour ſayd concerning the Chalice of the Euchariſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.27.</note> 
               <hi>Drinke ye all of this,</hi> the Pope (with no leſſe ſacriledge then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer) ſaith, Ye ſhall not all drinke of it; but, you Kings and Prieſts, drinke ye onely of it: As for all the reſt, they muſt be content to take the Communion in one kinde onely. I am often deeply touched with admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and adore with reuerence &amp; humility, the infinit patience, &amp; incomprehenſible long ſuffering of God; who, in a ſort ouercomming himſelfe, can with-hold his reuenging hand, from ſending down fire from hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen, or making the earth to open, for the puniſhing ſuch abhominable &amp; <hi>Luciferian</hi> pride of the <hi>Romane Antichriſt:</hi> When as he hath of old ſtricken King <hi>Vz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zah</hi> with ſodaine death, for only daring with his hand to touch and ſet vpright the Arke of the Couenant, when it tottered by reaſon of the vnruly motion of the Oxen that bare it: which Arke was a figure of this holy Sacrament.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I cannot but acknowledge, that I was wont to be inflamed with no ſmall indignation, as often as I thought vpon this Ring-leader of Hypocrites, who ſtiling himſelfe <hi>The ſeruant of the ſeruants of God,</hi> doth notwithſtanding beleeue, and teach. That the power and authority of Kings ouer their Subiects, is only of
<pb facs="tcp:1256:6"/>humane and poſitiue right: but, as for him ſelfe, h vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the words of our Sauiour, <hi>All power in heauen and in earth is giuen to me,</hi> (as if this had beene ſpoken of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi>) challengeth by diuine right, a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of depoſing Kings excommunicated by him; of diſpenſing with their Subiects in their Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance; of appointing thoſe Kings to bee ſlaine by whom he ſhall thinke good: ſo that all this while, this <hi>Deſtroyer</hi> will haue neither himſelfe, nor any other, that commit ſuch horrible and diſmall parricides, to be accounted murtherers; but rather iudgeth, that the maſſacring of all the Kings of the earth is not ſo great a miſchiefe, as that for the preuenting thereof, there ſhould be ſuffred a diſcloſure of any one thing related in auricular confeſſion; which ſo rigorous inſtitution of Confeſſion, is an inuention of his owne. Verily of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten muſing of theſe things.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Amaz'd I ſtood, my hayre did ſtart vpright:<note place="margin">Virgil.</note>
               </l>
               <l>My voyce durſt not come forth for deepe affright.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Vpon theſe and other like motiues, I decreed &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to depart out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> as ſoon as euer I could get any cleanly opportunity. Yet was there remaining one euill ſpirit vnconquered by me, which bare a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrong hand ouer me; and that was doating adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> a diſeaſe which had long bin my boſome-darling, and being bredde in my bones, would very hardly come out of my fleſh. So deepe a <hi>deuoto</hi> of our Lady was I, ſo duly and daily did I pray vnto her, ſo reuerently was I woont to adore and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorne
<pb facs="tcp:1256:7"/>her Images (whereof I had no leſſe then ſixe or ſeuen to furniſh my Chamber,) offering vnto them ſometime Flowers, otherwhile the choiſeſt fruites I could get; and withall, very frequently vſing thoſe words in the <hi>Romane Breuiary,</hi> fraught with blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: <hi>Haile Queene, the Mother of mercy, All haile our life, our ioy, our hope.</hi> And, <hi>O thou our Aduocate, turne vnto vs thoſe thine eyes full of pitty.</hi> And thoſe, <hi>Free vs from all danger thou bleſſed euer-virgin, thou happy gate of heauen, thou Queene of heauen, thou Miſtreſſe of the whole world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I was ſo deeply dyed heerewith, that I had much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe to quit my ſelfe of this habite, which I had gotten by ſo many and ſo feruent actions of this kinde: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould I euer haue ſhaken it off, vnleſſe I had with many teares &amp; prayers, for long time craued aſſiſtance at Gods hands: who being thus called vpon, did in his mercy heare me, and ſet me free from this ſpirit of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, in this manner. The ouer-ſight and care of the Library of our <hi>Monaſtery,</hi> beeing committed to my charge, ſo that no man could, but by my leaue, bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, or carry any booke out of the Librarie into his Camber. I was wont euery Saterday, to view ouer all the books, &amp; to ſet euery of them in his order. Which when I did according to my cuſtome, I found one time vnder a deske, amongſt ſome caſt bookes, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Spaniſh booke bearing this Title.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Two Treatiſes.</p>
               <p>The first, concerning the Pope and his Authority.</p>
               <p>The ſecond, concerning the Maſſe, and the holines thereof.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1256:7"/>
At the firſt ſight, I thought this book to haue beene made by a Papiſt, but aſſoone as I had read ouer the Epiſtle to the Reader, I was taken with more ioy then I was able to expreſſe. I iudged that I had found no ſmall treaſure, I kept it as a moſt precious pearle, I ſhewed it to no man, I read it all ouer. Among other things, I found there a certain hiſtory taken out of <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themius,</hi> in manner following.</p>
            <p>In the yeere of our Lord, 1470. one <hi>Allen of the Frocke</hi> a Dominicall Friar, deuiſed and compoſed the <hi>Roſary of our Lady,</hi> which, neglecting the Goſpel of our Lord and Sauiour, hee preached abroad; and ſo this Booke was publiſhed, wherein are related many my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> wrought by vertue of this <hi>Roſary.</hi> A little after the beginning, the Authour tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth a Tale, that, <hi>Once vpon a time, the bleſſed Virgin Mary came into the Chamber or cell of this Friar</hi> Allen; <hi>and hauing made a ring of a locke of her owne haire, ſhe, by deliuery of it, betroathed her ſelfe vnto him, kiſſed him, and offered to him her paps to be handled, and ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him, and finally conuerſed with this ſweete Fryar</hi> Allen <hi>as familiarly as the ſpouſe is wont to doe with her mate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who hath the patience to read, or heare this? Out vpon ſuch ribald blaſphemies, and blaſphemous ribal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dries! Verily I bluſh for ſhame, whilſt I write out theſe things. But I yeelde from my heart all praiſe to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty GOD, for that preſently vpon reading this homely Tale, the former deuotion which I bare to the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> grew key-cold. The truth is, I preſently beheld a certaine new light ſhining out of the Goſpel
<pb facs="tcp:1256:8"/>of our Sauiour, whence I was fully inſtructed, that we haue onely one <hi>Aduocate with God the Father,</hi> namely, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.1.</note> but as for an <hi>Aduocatreſſe,</hi> we finde there no newes of any ſuch. Euer ſince this, my life ſeemed irkeſome vnto me, becauſe I had no fit opportunity to make an eſcape, and to repaire to ſome place, where I might freely publiſh that Religion, which I had enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained into my heart. I was then ſurprized with a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent diſeaſe of that ſort which we Phyſitians, call <hi>acute per decidentiam.</hi> In the height, &amp; conſiſtence of which ſickneſſe, I vowed vnto God, that (if I recouered) I would forthwith adioyne my ſelfe vnto the true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, <hi>which worſhip God in ſpirit and truth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.23.</note> As ſoone as I made this vow, I began to recouer, and for the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner regaining of my health, I did get leaue to goe to the place where I was borne, and to remaine there for two months. Thither I went, there I remained, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered my perfect health. This my appointed time being expired, my Father, brethren, and kinsfolk thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that I had returned to our Monaſtery, I conueied my ſelfe to a Port in the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea, called <hi>Caulibre:</hi> there I tooke ſhip, &amp; thence went too <hi>Rome,</hi> with intent to ſee whither Chriſtian Religion do flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh more in that City, which is called the Head of the world, then in <hi>Spaine;</hi> as alſo that I might beholde the worlds wonders, which are at <hi>Rome,</hi> which if I had not ſeene, verily I ſhold haue euer longed to behold them. What ſhall I ſay? Scarſe found I in <hi>Rome</hi> any thing, that did not giue me offence and ſcandall. What is there at <hi>Rome,</hi> that filleth all mens eyes and eares, but the <hi>Popes</hi> diuine power, the <hi>Popes</hi> Holineſſe, the <hi>Popes</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1256:8"/>Indulgency, Pardons and Iubilees? Nothing at Rome is trumpeted out with more ful mouth, then <hi>the moſt Holy Father, the Head of the Church, God vpon earth.</hi> But as for the <hi>ſeauen headed Beaſt,</hi> that is, (by the Angels interpretation) <hi>ſeuen-hilled City;</hi> and as for that <hi>Woman,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 17.9.</note> 
               <hi>with whom the Kings of the earth haue committed fornication,</hi> that is (by the ſame interpretation) that <hi>great City,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 17.28.</note> 
               <hi>which hath dominion ouer the Kings of the earth;</hi> of theſe and ſuch like Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies, bent directly enough againſt the grand-children of <hi>Romalus,</hi> there is no newes now to be heard among the <hi>Romanes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Walking there, &amp; viewing the Churches, Lord, what ougly ſuperſtition doe I behold? As one waue crowdeth another, ſo doe their new <hi>Saints</hi> ſhoulder out the olde. A freſh yeſterdaies <hi>Saint</hi> there is, that hath already gotten three new Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches at <hi>Rome,</hi> new built and founded vnto him, and their wals from top to the floare garniſhed with pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures and tablets, dedicated to him. Of this vpſtart I would not ſpeake, if the Romanes would at any time leaue ſpeaking of him, and ceaſe with ſo lowd throats to call vpon him; if all places did not ring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with his name: nay if this <hi>Saintling</hi> did not beat and baniſh out of the Churches not onely <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> (which perhaps ſeemeth a ſmall matter to the Romaniſts) but alſo the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> her ſelfe. <hi>Francis</hi> and <hi>Anthony,</hi> and all the reſt of the Saints of the higher forme. <hi>Charles</hi> the Emperor, who of old was called <hi>Charles the Great,</hi> becauſe he
<pb facs="tcp:1256:9"/>vanquiſhed the <hi>Saracens,</hi> muſt now come downe, and be called <hi>Charles the little,</hi> in compariſon of this new <hi>Charles Borrhomaeus</hi> who thus triumpheth, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing put to flight, not his enemies, but his friends and fellow-Saints. And why may not we thus by way of reprehenſion mocke at the common moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kery of the world? but now it is time for me to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken out of this extaſie.</p>
            <p>I remained in <hi>Rome</hi> about a Month, all which while ſtill me thought I heard the voyce of Chriſt ſaying vnto me, <hi>Come forth, come forth out of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</hi> I come out on Gods name, and paſſe ouer to <hi>Mompelier,</hi> where <hi>God ſhewed me his aboundant mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in the middeſt of his Church, and ſtrengthened my heart with the grace of his holy ſpirit:</hi> So that eight yeares ſithence I there put off my Monkiſh cowle, and abiuring the groſſe errors of the Romiſh Church, I did publikly embrace the vndefiled faith of the true and Reformed Religion, not without the expreſſe ioy of (in a manner) all that City. And becauſe I could not then ſpeake the French tongue, I did by the aduice of all the Paſtors there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply my ſelfe not to the holy miniſtery (which my loſſe I yet with many ſighes deplore) but vnto my olde intermitted ſtudy of <hi>Phyſicke.</hi> But behold, while I was thus ſayling in the depths of <hi>Hyppocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> a violent tempeſt ouertaketh me, and that was this.</p>
            <p>My Father, a man ſpent with age, (being foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore yeeres olde) and taking it very heauily that I
<pb facs="tcp:1256:9"/>had fled to the enemies of faith, and heretiques (ſo they dreamingly deeme of vs) ſent to <hi>Monpelier</hi> one of my elder Brethren, together with a Coſen Germane of mine, Prieſt; both who for the ſpace of eight daies did beleager mee, firſt with faire intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and plentifull teares, then with Arguments drawne from Diuinity and Philoſophy; thirdly by rewards and offers of worldly goods; laſtly, by threats and terrible obiurgations, to beate mee off from my found intent, and holy reſolution. I think it not amiſſe heere to relate their language.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt (ſaid they) twelue Neeces now mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ageable, which will neuer get husbands ſo long as thou remaineſt an hereticke; for thoſe, who before were willing to marry them, now ſtart backe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; God forbid that we ſhould take to wife thoſe that are a-kin to an Hereticke: Returne, returne to our religion, if not for conſcience, (for we know that you are a lerned man, and haue not raſhly; nor without ſhew of reaſon left vs,) yet for the honor of our ſtocke and blood, which thou haſt branded with the foule ſpot of infamy, by forſaking the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> Church, &amp; embracing a new religion, which with all the Profeſſors thereof, (for they are but a few in number) the <hi>King of Spaine</hi> is reſolued to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſh and ruinate. Returne therefore to the holy Mother Church, at leaſt for the loue and reuerence you owe to our aged Father: who, euer ſithence the time hee heard that you were become an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, lieth ſicke and bed-ridde, pining away with griefe and ſorrow.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1256:10"/>
Heereto I anſwered as became a Chriſtian. But becauſe they would giue mee no patient audience, nor affoord themſelues any time to weigh my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, I vſed a very honeſt ſlight to bring my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the houſe of <hi>Falcarius</hi> a very worthy Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Gods Word, who for the ſpace of an whole houre did make a cleere demonſtration of the falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of the Romiſh religion, and truth of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, out of the <hi>Tenets</hi> of them both.</p>
            <p>My brother making obiection of nouelty againſt the Reformed religion, and want of Calling and of Antiquity in <hi>Caluin</hi> and <hi>Beza,</hi> and other ſuch like Paſtors; M. <hi>Falcarius</hi> according to his admirable faculty, made anſwere: Sir, What Religion call you new? ours? you are farre wide. Our Religion is the moſt ancient; if the Goſpell of our Sauiour, if the Epiſtles of <hi>Paul,</hi> and of other the Apoſtles (in a word) if the new Teſtament, if the Prophets, and the whole old Teſtament do teach the true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, needs muſt you confeſs that our religion is moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient; for we beleeue nothing, but that which wee reade in the old and new Teſtament, &amp; that which is drawen thence by neceſſary conſequence. Call your Religion, I pray you, call it new. For almoſt euery Pope, when hee commeth new into the <hi>Chaire,</hi> doth impoſe vpon you new precepts, and traditions, taken out of his vnwritten word, to bee beleeued and awefully obſerued by you, vnder paine of mortall ſinne: and what lawes one Pope layeth vpon you to be kept, as ſoone as hee is gone
<pb facs="tcp:1256:10"/>his way by diſeaſe, or by poyſon, another doth cancell.<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>26.</hi> Paul. <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> Is not the Communion vnder both kinds very ancient; being inſtituted by our Sauiour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? We with the primitiue Church, and with the moſt ancient Fathers, doe retaine the ſame, and acknowledge both kindes to be neceſſary to the eſſence of this Sacrament. Is not the worſhip of idols, and images a new thing? and forbidden ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inſtantly in the ſecond Commandement of the decalogue? We obey this diuine prohibition, but ye obey the Pope, commanding adoration of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages againſt the expreſſe Word of God. Is not the doctrine of <hi>Tranſubstantiation.</hi> a nouelty crept into the <hi>Romane</hi> Church, not aboue foure hundred yeeres agoe? This we conſtantly reiect, becauſe it is repugnant to Gods word, implieth a thouſand contradictions, and maketh thoſe to be Idolaters, that are at Maſſe. Thoſe words in the Scripture, <hi>This is my body,</hi> are to be vnderſtood in the ſame ſenſe and manner with thoſe, <hi>That Rocke was Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4. that is to ſay, a Sacramentall pledge, whereby Chriſt was repreſented, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited to them. Or as thoſe words of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch <hi>Ioſeph</hi> expounding <hi>Pharaohs</hi> dreame, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41. <hi>v.</hi> 26. <hi>Thoſe ſeauen faire kine, are ſeauen yeeres:</hi> Where the word <hi>Are,</hi> is by the conſent of all the Doctors taken for <hi>ſignifie.</hi> The ſame Patriarch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding the dreame of <hi>Pharaohs Butler;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 40.12.</note> 
               <hi>Thoſe three branches, are three dayes;</hi> that is, <hi>doe ſignifie them,</hi> when as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Ye are the body of
<pb facs="tcp:1256:11"/>Christ, and members in particular;</hi> are we therefore tranſubſtantiated into the very body of Chriſt? are not theſe ſpeeches ſpiritually to bee vnderſtoode? hereto may be added, that the <hi>Hebrew</hi> tongue hath no verbe which ſignifieth to <hi>ſignifie,</hi> and therefore inſtead thereof, vſeth the verbe ſubſtantiue, <hi>Sum.</hi> Therefore our Sauiour ſpeaking vulgarly, could not ſay, this ſignifieth my body, but inſtead there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſaid, <hi>This is my body.</hi> Which of the Fathers that floriſhed the firſt fiue hundred yeeres after Chriſt, did euer beleeue that we are iuſtified by the works of the Law, and not by Faith, as the holie Ghoſt ſpeaketh by the mouth of Saint <hi>Paul; Therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing iuſtified by faith, we haue peace with God?</hi> Which of the ancient Fathers haue conſtantly maintained any other Purgatorie, whereby our ſoules ſhould be purged before they enter into Heauen, but the blood of our Lord and Sauiour, who, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>By himſelfe purged our ſinnes?</hi> Who, as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Loued vs, and waſhed vs from our ſinnes by his owne blood;</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> againe, <hi>If the blood of Bulles and Goates, and the aſhes of an Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, ſprinkling the vncleane, ſanctifieth to the purify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the fleſh; how much more ſhall the bloude of Chriſt, who through the eternall Spirit, offered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe without ſpot to God, purge your conſcience from dead workes to ſerue the liuing God?</hi> Who euer of the Ancients, for the firſt fiue hundred, nay ſixe hundred yeares did beleeue, or teach, that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is the head of the vniuerſall Church,
<pb facs="tcp:1256:11"/>hauing power to depriue Kings of their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, to aſſoile Subiects from their ſworne Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, and to diſpenſe with Vowes lawfully made vnto God, to admit whom he pleaſe into the cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of Saints, to impoſe lawes vpon the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Church; to pardon ſinnes as a Iudge, to ſet free foules out of Purgatorie, to pronounce abſolute, and ſupreame iudgement, without all poſſibility of appeale, in matters appertaining vnto Faith? ſo that he may auouch himſelfe to bee out of all ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of errour, and heereupon that he might law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully bee called, by the high ſtyle of diuine Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, the Spouſe of the Church, and a god vppon earth?</p>
            <p>This, and much more to that purpoſe was elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently vrged, in the hearing of my ſaide Brother, by Maiſter <hi>Falcarius,</hi> cutting downe the tares of errours, by the ſharpe ſickle of his Arguments, whereby he drew teares from my Brothers eyes. And yet all this notwithſtanding, when my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did ſee mee ſo firmely ſetled in the Religion which I haue now vndertaken, that hee could no whit preuaile to draw me backe, about foure dayes after, he returned homeward full of ſorrow, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with my Coſen, no leſſe loaden with greefe; my ſelfe the while with dry eyes, and chearefull ſpirit, beholding them at their departure.</p>
            <p>Two yeeres after this, I tooke the degree of Batchelar in Phyſicke, in the famous Vniuerſity of <hi>Monpelier:</hi> and three yeeres after that, hauing em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed
<pb facs="tcp:1256:12"/>my time in ſtudying and practiſing Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, I was promoted <hi>Doctor</hi> in that faculty, in the flouriſhing Vniuerſitie of <hi>Valence</hi> in <hi>Daulphinee,</hi> not in the ordinary curſory forme, but paſſing the rigor of examination, as appeareth by my Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall Letters.</p>
            <p>Hauing taken this degree, I practiſed Phyſicke, neere vnto <hi>Monpelier,</hi> and in other parts of <hi>France,</hi> being rewarded by publique penſion, and (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I boaſt not) with good meaſure of reputation: So that by the bleſſing of God (to whom onely be the honor) I atchieued many cures of diſeaſes, hard to be iudged of, and almoſt vncurable.</p>
            <p>Whilſt I practiſed Phyſique, at Saint <hi>Giles,</hi> neere <hi>Niſmes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Niſmes. Arles.</note> and <hi>Arles</hi> vpon publique penſion, there did betide me that which I am willing to relate for Gods glory. There preached in that Citie a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Iudaite</hi> (I ſhould prophane the moſt bleſſed name, if I ſhould ſtile that ſect by the name of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite</hi>) a man eloquent enough, but aboue meaſure clamorous and ſpitefull againſt thoſe of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med religion: This man (by name <hi>Rampala</hi>) in his Sermon vpon All Saints day, expounding the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere made vpon that queſtion of S. <hi>Iohn, Who are thoſe that are clothed in white robes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 7.8.9. &amp; 13.</note> 
               <hi>and whence came they? Theſe are they which came out of great tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and waſhed their robes, and made them white in the bloud of the Lambe.</hi> Heere Sir <hi>Rampala</hi> layeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him in this manner: O my beloued ſoules, take heede leſt ye be ſeduced; conſider, I pray you,
<pb facs="tcp:1256:12"/>the anſwer of the Angel, he ſaith not,<note place="margin">It was use the Angel, but one of the Elders.</note> theſe are they which came out of faith onely, which is the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Hugonots</hi> (ſo they call the Reformed Chriſtians in <hi>France</hi>) but which came out of great Tribulation. Let vs not therefore bee Infidels, like the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> among whom there is no Sacrament to be found, no repentance, no good workes; which laſt wordes, this valiant Actor thundred out with ſhameleſſe confidence, and ſet them forth with the Theatricall Ornament, of clapping his handes one againſt the other.</p>
            <p>After Sermon, three or foure Papiſts of my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, asked me how I liked this <hi>Rampala:</hi> wherto I anſwered, that hee might be an eloquent man, but ſurely he was vterly ignorant of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of faith: which is euident, in that he imputed to vs a Doctrine cleane contrary to that which we profeſſe. Forſooth we haue neuer a Sacrament. What a lowde lye is this? we haue both the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which were inſtituted by our Sauiour, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, &amp; the holy Supper: but as for the other fiue, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> calleth Sacraments vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her owne inuention, we deeme them no better then baſtards. He ſaid that we haue no repentance: This is very falſe. We beleeue the Goſpell, enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning repentance in thoſe words,<note place="margin">Luke 13, 3 Mat. 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>Vnleſſe ye repent, ye ſhall periſh;</hi> and againe, <hi>Repent, for the Kingdome of heauen is at hand.</hi> Our Miniſters do daily inculcate vnto vs theſe words of the Goſpell, <hi>Exhorting vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:1256:13"/>repentance, and requiring the ſame.</hi> He ſaid that we make noaccount of goodworks. This is a meere ſlander.</p>
            <p>We beleeue with <hi>Bernard,</hi> that good works are the way to the Kingdome of Heauen, but not the cauſe of our reigning in that Kingdome.<note place="margin">Lib. 4. de Iuſti. cap. 1.</note> Wee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge (&amp; this your Maſter <hi>Bellarmine</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth by vs) that good workes are neceſſary vnto ſaluation, not that they are the efficient or merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious cauſes thereof, (for the free mercy of God, for the merits of Chriſts paſſion by faith in him, doth procure, and bring forth that ſaluation in vs;) but becauſe they doe teſtifie the ſame, and are liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly euidences thereof. Nay moreouer, we beleeue that iuſtifying faith cannot by any meanes ſubſiſt without good workes, which if they be wanting in any man, we (with Saint <hi>Iames</hi> the Apoſtle) call his faith a dead faith.<note place="margin">Iam. 2.20.27.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rampala,</hi> when it was told him what I had ſaid, became my enemy, &amp; hated me. The Gouernor of that City, being an honeſt an learned Gentleman, (and though himſelfe following the Popiſh parts, neither a perſecuter, nor a contemner of thoſe of the Reformed Religion) intreated me to come to his garden, and to bring with me ſome one of my own Religion, that there I might confeſſe with <hi>Rampala,</hi> either by oppoſing, or anſwering; I anſwered the ſaid Gouernour, that I tooke kindely his offer, and would be ready to encounter <hi>Rampala</hi> there. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly
<pb facs="tcp:1256:13"/>I came, accompanyed with one whom I choſe of the Reformed Religion, by name Maſter <hi>Marcot</hi> an Apothecary (a learned, honeſt and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous man:) there we expected <hi>Rampala</hi> diuers times to meet vs in that field, but no <hi>Rampala</hi> appeared. It ſeemeth his ſtomacke ſerued him not to enter the liſts, or to ſhew his face, in the preſence of <hi>a Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Spaniard.</hi> But what did his Worſhip? he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed a certaine Popiſh Swaſh-buckler, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the ſame City of Saint <hi>Giles,</hi> had ſlaine a man in the ſtreet. Him hee ſuborned to doe me ſome notable affront: and accordingly this knaue taking a very ſleight occaſion, gaue me a blow on the care in the open ſtreet. Theſe are the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding arguments of the <hi>Iudaits;</hi> this their open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handed rhetorique: this their cloſe fiſt of Logique. Nor muſt we thinke this ſtrange in thoſe who ſet forth cut throats for their Champions.</p>
            <p>What ſhould poore I doe in this caſe? I did poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket vp this wrong as patiently as I could; and when I had ſpent out my yeare there, I craued leaue to be gone, and that by the good aduice of a certaine friend, who wiſhed me to quit that place, affirming vpon his knowledge that the Papiſts there did lay wait for me. Being to depart, our brethren of the Reformed Church there held me, and earneſtly intreated mee to ſtay; but on the other ſide ſome tenne or fifteene Papiſts triumphed at my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, as though it had beene a ſigne of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt
<pb facs="tcp:1256:14"/>ouer me. So departed I according to our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours precept,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.23.</note> 
               <hi>If they perſecute you in one Citie, flye into another,</hi> and was entertained in other Towns, where I receiued conuenient ſtipend, namely, in <hi>Bouuer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bouuer. Kaylaz.</note> and <hi>Kaylaz,</hi> neere vnto <hi>Niſmes,</hi> whoſe inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants were all proteſtants.</p>
            <p>Whileſt I remained here, I read ouer againe and againe, a certaine French Treatiſe written by M. <hi>Peter Moulin,</hi> called, <hi>The Buckler of Faith.</hi> In it, I found many things which did cleare vnto mee the Doctrine of ſaluation: vpon which paſſages I did dayly meditate, and oftentimes ſaide to my ſelfe thus: O yee my brethren <hi>Spanyards,</hi> whom God hath indued with ſuch depth of wit; O would our Maſters, the Inquiſitors would ſuffer you to take this <hi>Buckler</hi> into your hands, to arme your ſelues with this ſhield againſt all the poiſonous darts of the malignant enemy. O would to God I might with loſſe of my life, buy the happineſſe to ſee you obey our Lord and Sauiour,<note place="margin">Iohn 5.39.</note> bidding vs <hi>ſearch the Scriptures,</hi> rather then yeeld vnto the yoke of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt,</hi> the Lord of Lords, who commandeth you the contrary; and taking the Scriptures from you, giueth you, inſtead thereof, ſtocks and ſtones, to be adored and worſhipped by you. O would to God that there might ſhine in your eyes, ſome glimpſe of that light, which guideth vs wretched men out of the <hi>kingdome of darkeneſſe, into the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious kingdome of the Sonne of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſ. 1.13.</note> O that the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:1256:14"/>good God, <hi>who is light, and in whom there is no dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Iohn 1, 5.</note> would ſay vnto you, that which he ſaid in the beginning, and ſtill ſaith to his elect,<note place="margin">Gen. 1, 3.</note> 
               <hi>Let there bee Light.</hi> Then ſurely you ſhould not any longer bee <hi>darkneſſe, but Light in the Lord:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephoſ. 5.8.</note> no longer wande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſheepe, falling downe before Idols, but <hi>retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the ſhepheard, and Byſhop of our ſoules,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2, 28</note> euen vnto Chriſt Ieſus, who is ready to <hi>betroath them vnto himſelfe</hi> by true faith, which worketh by cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 2, 25.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But there is one that hindreth you from enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this great benefit namely, he that will bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted another <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and omnipotent; and yet in the meane either ſtealeth from you, or chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth Gods Commaundements, and will by no means ſuffer you to read and heare the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in your Mother tongue, leaſt you ſhould vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them, and by the light of them, diſcouer his tyranny.</p>
            <p>Would to God that you that <hi>ſit in darkeneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 1, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; in the ſhadow of death,</hi> might bee enlightned by the <hi>Sun of righteouſneſſe ariſing vnto you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal 4, 2.</note> 
               <hi>that yee might go forth, and grow vp, as Calues of the ſtall,</hi> ſhaking off the Popes heauy yoak, which himſelfe wil not touch ſo much as with his finger; &amp; yeelding your neckes vnto the ſweet yoake of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I would to God, the Office of Inquiſition, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Inquination, would ſuffer you to view engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in this Buckler, a faire and pure Confeſſion of
<pb facs="tcp:1256:15"/>Faith, moſt agreeable to the Scriptures. Then ſhould you eaſily behold the falſhood, and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of your Religion, which you would thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on loath no leſſe then now you deteſt our Religion, being induced ſo to doe by your Preachers, who decipher it vnto you, as foule, falſe, and contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, as it is in it ſelfe faire, true, and amiable. Then ſhould you ſee as cleare as the noone day, That the Reformed Chriſtians or Proteſtants (whom ye call Heretiques, becauſe they will not thruſt their necks into the Popes tyrannous yoake) doe not, as you dreame, beleeue many things repugnant, not onely againſt the Word of God; but alſo againſt the light of reaſon. Your clamorous Friers in their ſermons, ring in your eares, that we beleeue the bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Marie,</hi> not to haue continued a Virgin after the birth of our Sauiour: That wee haue corrupted or diſmembred the Scriptures: That there be no Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments in our Churches; or at leaſt, that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that the Bread and Wine in the Sacrament of the Body and bloud of our Lord, are nothing elſe, but naked and barren ſignes: That we damne all good Workes: That we admit no penance. But, as for our perſons, your people being miſled, and incenſed by the barking of your Friers, thinketh that we beare not the ſhape of men, but are Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters with Dogges faces, or Hogges ſnowts: That we liue barbarouſly and wildely, in rude Cottages or Dennes. Theſe and ſuch like guls they put vpon
<pb facs="tcp:1256:15"/>you, which deſerue rather our Laughter in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, then our labour in refutation.</p>
            <p>As for that one point, concerning the raiſing a diſhonourable opinion of the Virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> let them looke to it, who bluſh not when they reade that, which before wee haue touched concerning worthy ſir <hi>Allen,</hi> ſo wooed &amp; courted by the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin.</p>
            <p>Conſidering and weighing with my ſelfe, all theſe particulars, and conferring with certaine lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and diſcreete Miniſters of Gods Word, as alſo with other well affected Gentlemen, vpon their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and intreatie, I was inflamed with a deſire, to tranſlate the aforſaid <hi>Buckler of faith,</hi> into the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh tongue. And being reſolued no longer to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the motion of Gods Spirit (which with ſorrow I confeſſe my ſelfe to haue reſiſted for the ſpace of a yeare) I ſet my hand to this taske; and hauing with foure moneths paines finiſhed it, I dedicated the ſame vnto the moſt Excellent <hi>Charles,</hi> Prince of <hi>Wales;</hi> being thereunto led by the firſt Author, by whom, the ſaide Treatiſe in the Originall French, was dedicated vnto his Highneſſe.</p>
            <p>But when as a certaine honeſt man of <hi>Monpeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> by whom I had ſent Letters into <hi>Spaine</hi> to my bretheren, vppon his returne thence, had with an Oath affirmed vnto mee, that hee heard my elder Brother ſpeake theſe words: <hi>All we his ſixe Brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren deſire nothing more erneſtly in the world the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his death</hi> (ſpeaking of me;) <hi>we would willingly giue a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb facs="tcp:1256:16"/>vnto any man, that would make an end of him.</hi> When I ſaw, that as long as I remained in <hi>France,</hi> I was in daily danger of my life, I betooke my ſelfe hither into <hi>England,</hi> as into the Hauen of ſafetie: with intent that my ſelfe, who had beene in <hi>Spain</hi> a bad Phyſitian of ſoules, in <hi>France</hi> by Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a good one of bodies; might in <hi>England</hi> becom a good Phyſitian in ſpecial to my ſelfe of body and ſoule, by ſecuring them both vnder the Gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the moſt gracious King <hi>Iames,</hi> the moſt po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>werful defender of the ſincere &amp; vnpolluted faith; reſoluing to yeeld all obedience vnto ſuch a King, profeſſing the Reformed Religion, and withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelfe from Papiſts (whoſe company is wont to breed infection) ſome-where within his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Dominions, either to exerciſe my function of Miniſtery, or to practiſe Phyſicke, and by one, or both of theſe to maintaine my ſelfe in diet &amp; cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, by my honeſt labor.</p>
            <p>Neither thought I fit to come hither vnarmed; and therfore brought I with me this <hi>buckler,</hi> which I haue already preſeted to that moſt noble Prince <hi>Charles</hi> the riſing Morning-Starre of <hi>Great-Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine:</hi> which my ſmall preſent, his Highneſſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his wonted gentleneſſe, did moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly accept. And now haue I learned by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that to be true which al the world witneſſeth, namely, that no eloquence can expreſſe that pietie towards God, and zeale for Gods houſe, which is
<pb facs="tcp:1256:16"/>found in the moſt mighty <hi>King of great Brittain,</hi> and the moſt excellent <hi>Prince,</hi> the liuely Image of his renowned Father, vpon both whom, Nature ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to haue powred out all her endowments and ornaments culled out from all others.</p>
            <p>But now I betake my ſelfe to you, Fathers of this Church; moſt Reuerend <hi>Archbiſhops;</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend <hi>Biſhops;</hi> Worſhipfull, and well-deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Doctors</hi> and <hi>Pastors;</hi> to you I addreſſe my ſelfe, who are the <hi>ſalt of the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.</note> 
               <hi>the light of the World, a City ſet vpon an hill:</hi> to this Synode I flye, as to a City of refuge; not as a Man-ſlayer, but contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, my ſelfe hauing of late very hardly eſcaped ſlaughter.</p>
            <p>Namely in the moneth of <hi>February</hi> lately paſt, being in London, and walking in <hi>Pauls,</hi> there mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth me, as by chance, one vnknowne to me, but certainely a ſlieknaue; who entering into confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with me about matter of Phyſicke, intreateth mee that I would take the paines to viſit a certaine woman which lay ſicke of a ſore diſeaſe, and forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of other Phyſitians, as vncureable. This hee diuers times vrged, ſoliciting me foure dayes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and promiſing me a large reward. Poore I, in my ſimple credulity yeelded thereto; he leades me along the ſtreetes for the ſpace of an howre and an halfe: then at length we finde the houſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſick woman; where, after much queſtioning &amp; conferring about her diſeaſe, I tarried ſupper vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:1256:17"/>on the intreaty of him that brought mee thither; who at Supper ſaid Grace in Latine. Preſently after eight of the clocke at night we depart thence. Then he, making as though he would (as hee had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) guide me backe to my chamber, leadeth mee cleane another way beyond the Citie wals, out of the broad ſtreets, through by-lanes and narrow al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, into deſert places, and into the fields. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time he ſtops his pace and ſtandeth ſtill, ſometimes he liſtneth carefully, and when I aske him the cauſe thereof; I liſten, ſaith he, to heare if any man come by, of whom I may aske the way to <hi>London,</hi> which verily I haue loſt, and know not where I am. But verily he lyed; for his liſtning was for nothing elſe, but that he might haue me ſure, to ſet vpon mee far enough from any to helpe me. I call God to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that, when I thus wandred with him in the darke, my mind did fore-boad ſome miſchance vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me; whereupon I lifted mine eyes to heauen, and armed my ſelfe as well as I could, with <hi>repentance towards God, and faith in our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 20.21.</note> Now then about ten of the clocke in the night, hauing gotten me into ſuch a place as he deſired, namely in the great fields called S. <hi>Iameſes,</hi> he on a ſudden flies vpon me with his naked dagger, and grieuouſly wounded me neere the left ventricle of the heart; from whence come thoſe two principall veſſels of life, the one called <hi>the veiny Artery,</hi> and the other <hi>Aorta:</hi> and preſently running away, left me there
<pb facs="tcp:1256:17"/>halfe dead. This wound being giuen me in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame cold night, and being in depth as much as eight fingers breadth, yet not directly, but oblique<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pearcing, was dangerous enough, eſpecially when as I knew not where I was, nor whom to call on for helpe, being vtterly ignorant of the Engliſh tongue: and ſurely I had neuer ſeene the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings light, had not a certaine good <hi>Samaritane</hi> that very night powred wine and oyle into my wound: that is, vnleſſe the renowned <hi>Doctor Mayern</hi> his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties moſt worthy principall Phyſition, being as much repleniſhed with mercy and charity, as with knowledge and experience, had reached forth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me his helping hand, and for three weekes ſpace entertained me in his houſe, had ſpeciall care of my recouery.</p>
            <p>Though this wound be healed, yet the ſcarre thereof remaineth, and euer will ſo long as I liue; whereof I am ſo farre from being aſhamed (it ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing been inflicted vpon me in hatred of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion) that I rather reioyce in it, &amp; ſay with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6. v. 17.</note> 
               <hi>I beare in my body the markes of the Lord Ieſus. Paphnutius,</hi> who was preſent at the Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> hauing one of his eyes boared out, and his ham-ſtrings cut, for his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant profeſſion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, was not thought to be deformed, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more beautified by theſe markes: Afford vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, I pray you reuerend Fathers, vnto me the meaneſt and baſeſt Profeſſor, yea and Confeſſor
<pb facs="tcp:1256:18"/>of the Chriſtian reformed Religion, a place in this your Synod, not by way of locall preſence, but by admiſſion into your good opinion, and fatherly loue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paphnutius</hi> after he had receiued thoſe prints and ſeales of Chriſtian conſtancy, ceaſed not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, and confeſſe Chriſt the more feruently: verily I am ſo farre from being diſcouraged by this dangerous conflict from walking ſtill in that path of pure Religion, which I haue ſet into, that this ſame Dagger is become a goade or ſpurre vnto me, whereby I am pricked on to runne more couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and ſwiftly in the reſt of that race, which I haue vndertaken. Now therefore, God thus put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting me forward, it the more behooueth mee to whet my pen againſt the errors of papiſtry, and to doe my beſt for maintaining the honour of all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches againſt the calumniations of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who are zealous, but not according to knowledge; and father vpon vs another manner of Confeſſion of faith, cleane contrary to that which we profeſſe.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I intreate all you Paſtors and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the reformed Churches, by the bowels of Gods mercies, to take eſpeciall care and order, that the true Confeſſion of your ſincere Faith may be made knowne to foraigne people, who are miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deceiued in this behalfe; namely, to that end there may be publiſhed ſome ſmall Treatiſes tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated
<pb facs="tcp:1256:18"/>or written in the vulgar languages of the people of <hi>Spaine, Italie, France,</hi> and other Nations. I, for my part, and poore faculty, am ready and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to imploy herein my paines by day and night, euen to my laſt gaſpe. This, this enterpriſe, I ſay, doth neerely concerne the glory of God, the ſauing of ſoules, the maintaining of the honour of the moſt gracious <hi>King of great Brittaine,</hi> defender of the Faith, as alſo the ſhielding of your own reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from the ſlanders of the Papiſts. Whoſe reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and forged calumniations againſt you, by no other meanes can be refuted, then by that courſe, which here is wiſhed, and offered by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Him, that againe recommends himſelfe to your charitable and fatherly embraces, <hi>Iohn de Nicholas &amp; Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charles, Doctor in Phyſicke.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
